Squarespace.
You’ve probably seen one
of their many YouTube sponsorships.
At one point, over 50% of revenue
went back into marketing.
It feels like this brand was
everywhere… but now, not so much.
So what happened?
This story is a bit different.
They didn’t have a rise and collapse
like other companies, something
genuinely unexpected happened.
They went public… without
an IPO, and raised no money.
And, then they went private again?
This is how Squarespace exploded,
then went to war with… itself.
If you don’t know Squarespace,
it’s a very popular, no-coding website builder.
Pick a template catered to your needs, tweak it,
and boom. You have a website.
But the origin of Squarespace,
is a little bit different.
Way back in 2003, Anthony Casalena,
a computer science major, built the first
version from his University of Maryland
dorm room, with a $30,000 loan from his parents.
[Anthony Casalena, Founder]: “I coded a blogging
tool that I wanted to use. It wasn't until a
friend said he'd pay for it that I realized
I could also build a company.”
Pretty normal so far,
but what isn’t, is how… sensible?
Over the next seven years, Squarespace grew to
$10 million in annual revenue, and 30 staff, with
no funding. Aside from that first 30k, of course.
But, they had reached a ceiling. To scale
up more, to reach more people, invest into
customer acquisition, they needed more money.
At this point, Getty Images tried to acquire
them. This would have given Squarespace the
backing they needed, Casalena rejected the offer.
Instead, he was going a very
different route: VC funding.
Accel and Index Ventures were
brought in, investing $38.5 million.
But, this was a bit different.
[Anthony Casalena, Founder]: “This
is a minority investment -- the same team
that has always managed Squarespace remains
in charge. This investment -- a growth stage
investment on top of an already successful
business -- will allow us to more rapidly
produce the sort of products we want to make,
and focus on getting those products to market.”
It’s quite often the case a startup begins to
explode, needs capital, and the founder
gives up control, then things deteriorate.
With new funding, Squarespace
began to scale, and quick.
In 2015 they had over 500 employees, and by 2017,
they had over $300 million in revenue, which
crazily, was up 50% year over year. Insane growth.
But the question is, how?
Around this time, other website
builders were popping up.
What made Squarespace
different, and grow so quickly?
Unlike Wix and many other companies that tried
to capture a massive free market, and convert on
that… Squarespace didn’t have a free tier.
No freemium model at all.
They positioned the brand around visual
quality, typography, “designer” templates,
and that “premium” experience. That
appealed strongly to photographers,
designers, restaurants, consultants, artists, etc.
Having to pay upfront reinforced this premium
idea. This is also why they positioned
themselves as more a creative tool,
than a regular website builder.
Campaigns used slogans like “build
it beautiful”. Less technical, more artsy.
But for their core customers, a great idea.
Plus, no free tier meant they
didn’t have to provide support
to customers who weren’t bringing in revenue.
Squarespace’s business model reinforced that
quality image. And, on that note, we need to
talk about Squarespace’s insane marketing.
It feels like the best LLM
to use changes every month.
But even just a few AI plans can add up
very quickly, especially with tokens.
So… why not have them all
for one $10 subscription?
This is Mammouth which gives you access to
most of the latest, cutting edge AI models.
All for $10 a month.
Mammouth is based in Paris,
with their servers hosted in Germany,
which means they are fully GDPR compliant
They keep absolutely no training data
But Mammouth is also the best way to use LLMs.
Their "re-prompting" feature lets you
compare models' responses in one click.
Click “reprompt”, and compare responses between
GPT, Claude, Gemini, Grok, or any other.
Every LLM has its own strengths, and
Mammouth gives you the best of all of them.
It also comes with specialty AI features, like
Perplexity Deep research, image and document
analysis, or voice dictation from GPT.
But with Mammouth.AI, you don’t need a
giant pile of subscriptions.
One of my favorite features
are their custom mammoths.
Create different mammoths with
their own instructions, but also their own icons.
This plan also gives you access to Mammouth API,
which allows you to integrate models
into your own automation tools.
Or if you’re a developer, put Mammouth
code directly in your coding console,
like Windows Powershell, VS Code, Cursor, or more.
Mammouth equips over 400 companies and public
administrations with its dedicated plan.
It has great plans for both
individuals and companies.
Stay at the cutting edge of AI without
the lock in, and less of the cost.
Click the url in the
description and try Mammouth today.
Thank you to Mammouth for sponsoring our videos.
Squarespace was putting a lot
of money back into marketing.
One of the biggest parts of
which was the Super Bowl.
Jeff Bridges in 2015, Key & Peele in 2016,
Keanu Reeves in 2018, Zendaya + André 3000
in 2022, Adam Driver in 2023, Martin
Scorsese in 2024, Emma Stone in 2026.
Not only are Super Bowl ads
expensive… but so are these actors.
But, it was quite important.
Squarespace wanted to become
a massive household brand.
[Anthony Casalena, Founder,
CEO of Squarespace]: the same year:
"We want people to have heard of us."
They weren’t the only ones either, Wix
was doing the same thing, and a bit of an
advertising arms race began between the two.
And that continued through Sponsorships.
All over YouTube, and in particular,
podcasts, which were starting to boom,
Squarespace and Wix were there.
[Ryan Stansky, Squarespace Marketing]: “Podcasting
has been a base for us that we’ve scaled
up over the years. And as our marketing
budget has grown each year, the podcast
budget has grown nearly proportionally.”
[Anthony Casalena, Founder, CEO
of Squarespace]: “The audience
of people who listen to podcasts are well
educated, sophisticated, entrepreneurial
and a really good audience for us.”
And, the results would speak for themselves.
So, if things were going so great, why did
they do an IPO, then delist the stock later?
Well, it turns out, they never did
an IPO… but something else entirely.
Which was smart, but came with a few risks.
By the end of financial year 2020, they had
$621 million in revenue, 60x growth over the
decade, and 50% compounding annual growth.
Subscriptions to Squarespace increased almost
23% in 2020 to 3.7 million. Keep in mind,
this was in the pandemic, and
everyone suddenly wanted a website.
Around this time, in April 2021,
Squarespace was preparing to go public.
But this is where things get a bit unusual.
Squarespace wasn’t doing an IPO.
However, they were going public on the NYSE.
But they wouldn’t be raising any money.
So… how? And why?
Isn’t the whole
point of going public, to raise more money?
This is quite different to a lot of tech startups.
Squarespace filed for a direct listing of
shares. This means no new shares were created,
instead, existing shares were registered.
This was actually very smart, for a few reasons.
First, VC investors could now sell.
Accel and Index invested in July 2010.
Venture funds want to exit at some point, to make
a return, and they’d been around quite a while.
This lets them sell their
existing stock, if they like.
Plus, Squarespace didn’t really need the money.
They had just raised another $300 million a
couple months earlier, which put
them at a $10 billion valuation.
[Anthony Casalena, Founder, CEO of Squarespace]:
“A direct listing fit for us because Squarespace
has been a profitable company for a number of
years and we don’t need to raise money in this
event. Our thinking was pursue the direct listing,
give people the option to buy if they want to buy,
sell if they want to sell. What’s great about
the direct listing is no one’s suffering
unnecessary dilution today.”
Squarespace was making money,
had a strong roadmap, and had strong
growth… Why dilute their shares?
And this was the bigger reason.
No new shares, ownership doesn’t change.
Casalena didn’t want to dilute the shares
and give up more control. And rightly so.
There were 49,086,410 shares of
Class B stock for Squarespace, which
represented “68.2% of the total voting power”.
And all of this, was held by Anthony Casalena,
either directly or across multiple trusts.
After all the VC rounds and even going public,
the founder of Squarespace, was still in control.
Though, this public listing, didn’t quite go as
planned, and brought an unexpected problem.
They were previously valued at $10 billion,
at $68.42 a share. This is when Tiger Global,
Dragoneer, D1, Fidelity, T. Rowe and Spruce
House invested in that $300 million raise.
But, this listing set Squarespace’s value
at just $6.6 billion. It opened at just $48.
As it turns out, this listing, would create
a massive point of tension between
Casalena, and the other shareholders…
And… why did they reverse course and
go private just a couple years later?
Well, immediately after
listing, some problems appeared.
Not only did the stock open below
expectations… it quickly tanked.
From $52 in May 2021, to just
$20 the same time next year.
Not great.
What happened?
To answer that, we first need to
look at some of their acquisitions.
In 2019 Squarespace bought Acuity Scheduling,
and then the social media content tool Unfold.
Then Tock in 2021, a restaurant reservation and
hospitality platform, for more than $400 million.
Then Google Domains in 2023, for $180 million
About 10 million domains, which would be
merged into Squarespace domains.
I can see the logic. Expand your
offering and assets to make Squarespace a
more “all in one” package for businesses.
But, these acquisitions didn’t really
add value in the way Squarespace hoped.
Revenue was beginning to slow.
In Q2 2021, on revenue of $196 million,
Squarespace had a net loss of $27.1
million, or $225.2 million if you
include a large write-down of Tock’s valuation.
Then for the 2022 financial year, an annual loss
of $252.2 million, on revenue of $867 million.
Then another net loss in 2023 of $7.1 million.
For all of 2022, revenue had grown just 10%. Not
terrible, but things were clearly slowing down.
So why did growth slow down?
And, why did Squarespace
eventually leave the NYSE?
Did they delist? Or did something else happen?
If you’ve watched this far, consider
subscribing! It helps the channel and
means you won’t miss future videos.
I think Squarespace hit its ceiling
just as Covid hit.
After the listing,
they were no longer benefiting from a fresh
wave of people discovering websites. They were
competing for slower, more expensive growth in
a crowded and increasingly commoditised market.
The website market was maturing, and slowing down,
and it was becoming more crowded. Meaning customer
acquisition costs were going up.
But Squarespace had a unique
problem to everyone else.
Squarespace had expanded into
ecommerce, scheduling, restaurant technology,
payments, enterprise, domains, and so much more.
I’m sure you know the phrase “Jack of all trades”…
Well, Squarespace was the master of none.
Not as commerce-focused as Shopify. Not
as open and extensible as WordPress.
Plus other acquisitions, like Google
Domains, didn’t really help with growth.
A domain customer… isn’t
necessarily a new website customer.
And the biggest case was Tock.
Not only did it have a huge
write-down, Squarespace sold Tock to
American Express for $400 million.
That might not sound like a big deal. Bought
for 400 mil, sold for 400 mil… but it is.
It means it wasn’t actually
adding value to Squarespace,
and as an asset, it wasn’t appreciating.
That cash could have gone somewhere else,
which did make a return.
And all this came to a head,
when Squarespace finally looked to leave the NYSE.
But it wasn’t delisting, it was a buyout.
This put Anthony Casalena at
odds with the other shareholders.
In May 2024, Squarespace agreed to be
acquired by UK private equity firm Permira,
in an all-cash deal valued at $6.9 billion.
“Squarespace stockholders will receive
$44.00 per share in cash”
Casalena actually had been
meeting with Permira as far back as late 2022
and he agreed to roll over most of his equity
and stay on as CEO and board chairman.
Sounds like a good exit… but
shareholders weren’t exactly thrilled.
Casalena would remain one of the largest
shareholders, while minority shareholders got
a fixed cash price, without much say in any
of it. And not a particularly great cash price.
Plus, while Squarespace approached a few private
equity firms, other companies weren’t approached
at all, because Casalena wanted to stay in charge.
“Despite the offer representing a premium at
announcement to historic trading levels and
valuation multiples, there appears to
be no downside risk of non-approval”.
Glazer Capital, LLC, one of the biggest minority
Squarespace shareholders, also published an open
letter to the board of directors.
[Glazer Capital, LLC]: “We strongly
believe that the Merger Consideration is
demonstrably inadequate and is the product
of a self-serving go-private process engineered
by a founder-CEO that presently controls,
and desires to retain control over, Squarespace's
destiny. It is also our view that the Acquisition
was orchestrated to deliver the Company into the
arms of a handpicked private equity consortium.
Accordingly, we intend to vote all of our
shares against this transaction at the
upcoming meeting of Squarespace shareholders.”
Permira returned with a revised offer. $46.50
per share, an increase of $2.50. But also,
a change to the structure of the deal.
In the first offer, Squarespace needed a
shareholder vote, which was mostly controlled
by a couple of individual investors and Casalena.
This time, Permira just offered to buy shares
directly. Once enough shareholders sold, the
rest were bought out automatically, at $46.50.
And this time, it went through.
Squarespace, was now private again.
Squarespace is still around today,
you may even see it in a sponsorship.
But growth has slowed dramatically.
Now, they’re competing against a new competitor.
Not so much Wix or WordPress, but AI.
Vibe-coded websites. No need for templates.
Now they’re investing into R&D and AI to keep up.
But Squarespace’s best chance against this,
is their most valuable asset: their brand.
That high quality association they’ve spent
years building, across so many
sponsorships and Super Bowls.
But this is an ongoing battle.
Only time will tell if Squarespace
can survive this new opponent.
Their long-term rival, Wix,
is also wrestling with these challenges.
But, they don’t have quite the same beloved brand.
In fact, some of their marketing
led them to annoy customers,
and into some weird drama with WordPress.
Click here to learn the other side of the story.